[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software so I'm sitting here with
Matilda pod at Jack's conference and we
want to talk about the project called
flux so Martin welcome to the show and
Aaron say a few words about yourself
hey welcome my name is Martin D but I
work for pivotal let's company behind
spring and groovy grades rabbitmq
Reddy's Cloud Foundry and a few other
awesome projects I think and I'm working
on the spring tool suite so I'm kind of
the one of the tooling guys inside
inside pivotal and in our team we do all
these kind of Eclipse integrations for
project XYZ like spring integration for
Eclipse and Gradle integration and
groovy integration and things like that
and I'm also thinking about this kind of
next-generation tooling and where should
the developer tooling we should that be
in in a few years from now okay sounds
quite interesting so and we want to talk
about this project called flux so can
you try to say a few words about that
project what the goals are why you
decided to do it who is behind it and so
on yeah sure
project flux is a new project at Eclipse
so it's an eclipse project just being
created a few weeks ago and the idea
behind project flux is it tries to solve
two different problems at the same time
and one problem is we are thinking about
moving developer tooling into the cloud
so a little bit away from the
traditional desktop IDE into something
that's
browser-based cloud-based and we do not
know exactly at the moment how this
developer tooling will look like in the
future the feeling that we have is it
will not exactly be the desktop IDE just
running inside a browser window that
doesn't make much sense I think even
though you might see some of those
approaches in cloud based IDE Z at the
moment that are emerging but I think
it's not the exact right idea for
designing and implementing developer
tooling for the cloud and with project
flux we are trying to give an answer to
that in combination with how should this
cloud-based developer tooling be
implemented so that's the the first
thing we're trying to solve and the
second thing is that if you take a look
at the existing cloud-based developer
tooling you usually have the situation
that you you have to decide whether you
would like to continue to use your
existing desktop ID ease and their
desktop tools or you jump over the wall
and you use tools that are running
inside the cloud and everything in that
case everything is inside the cloud your
files inside the cloud other tools are
inside the cloud the only window to
access all that stuff is a browser
window usually so there's something
missing in between because typically
these clubbers at least they are not yet
as feature-rich as existing desktop IDE
they maybe do not support the languages
you would like to use and you would have
to throw away all your local files and
all your local tools right so you would
maybe miss your command line tool and
things like that and I think this
either-or decision is not the right way
to approach this this problem and
therefore project flux is building a
bridge a bridge between the desktop IDE
and the cloud based developer tooling so
that we have a very smooth migration
path from today's tester by the ease
doing Java development towards cloud
based IDE or cloud based developer
tooling that might also already support
Java to a certain degree or more in the
future or support different languages
but you can you can decide everyday what
tool to use and you can switch between
both worlds in a very seamless way so
that you can work with in the end with
both tools on the same project at the
same time if you want and you do not
have to decide which way to go right and
then you'll leave everything behind
kind of the that's a the vision behind
that it may be that you just start or
you continue to use it as to write E and
then you started using
a little bit of the club is twirling in
addition to that a little bit more over
time and maybe one day you wake up and
think huh well I haven't started my
decimide a whole week that must be it
must be a good sign maybe that I can use
the cloud-based tooling only maybe or
maybe we do not end up there maybe we
stop somewhere in between and say how
for certain tasks it may be still make
sense to use in desktop IDE and desktop
tooling and you should be able to
continue to do that in addition to
cloud-based tooling and flux is building
this bridge between that it kind of it
merges those two worlds together into
one view into one one kind of system and
it doesn't it doesn't make a huge
difference if you use club is tooling or
the your desktop IDE for your projects
it becomes kind of the same and you can
can move forth and back and migrate very
smoothly between those two worlds and
those are the two I think the two
challenges we're trying to solve with
project flux and we started that project
a while a girl inside pivotal when we
thought about what should come what
should comes next as Podesta by the ease
where should we go we did a bunch of
prototypes and tried out different
things so we worked on this project
called scripted where we did a
JavaScript editor for browser and there
are other projects in that area like
Eclipse Orion and other things and we we
always thought that hmm it's pointing
towards the right direction but it's not
really solving the exact right problem
and with flux we have the feeling and
the first feedback that we got is this
is exactly pointing and into the right
direction and doing the exact right
thing so that's that's a I think it
brief over you but what flux is in what
flux is about okay so as you said it's
it's a rich between my desktop ID and
cloud based routing so what are you
imagine could be the first flower that I
would use I mean would I do my compile
step in the cloud or would I someone run
the debugger in the cloud or what what
are you imagine would that look like
where are the components that I
integrate and
how does that burn yeah the the idea and
the product of that we implement for
project flux at the moment is that you
first you continue to use it as the yte
as it is right there's no need to change
anything and in addition to that you can
connect your project to the cloud and
this is something like let's say like
Dropbox for code so everything stays
locally on your hard drive it's all on
your machine but in addition to that
it's kind of mirrored and synced to the
cloud so that you can in addition to
work with your desktop IDE on your local
files you can also open up a web browser
and edit your code and browse your code
and that I think is kind of the first
step right
so you can you can just open a web
browser from anywhere in the world and
look at your code and and edit your code
and in addition to that enhancing these
code editors that's running inside the
browser window and will be I think the
next step and we already did did a few
things to watch this kind of more
advanced code editing to support
advanced languages like Java so compiled
languages not these kind of scripting
languages where you usually don't have
much tooling so that you are able to
edit your code in kind of the same way
as in a desktop IDE so while you're
typing you're getting errors and
warnings you get content assist all the
time and real Java countenance is for
example and you can navigate you can do
reflect rings
you can you can jump to different files
you can jump to the Declaration and all
those nice features that you really like
even even even quick fixes for oh
there's an error like I get quick fixes
and getting that all that in in in a
real time in real time fashion so that
it really feels like an awesome code
editor that's running inside the browser
we know that that I'm not aware of that
does exist at the moment for these kind
of compiled languages for a
browser-based environment and I think
those are those those will be the first
steps and the next steps will of course
be supporting more languages and and
doing more sophisticated stuff that is
maybe very interesting to do in the
cloud like
executing unit tests all the time maybe
or working on a piece of cold
collaboratively or connecting your
things to to apply form as a service
environment where you can just deploy
your stuff all the time from the cloud
and things like that that a lot of ideas
and I can share about one a few of those
ideas in more detail later but I think
those are the first steps I think we
were trying to do so that you can
continue use it as by the e you started
working on your code browsing you know
your projects in the in the web editor
and then adding more and more services
to these webby world so that it will be
kind of in the end you can basically you
should be able to do everything from the
from the browser-based editor and from
the browser-based environment it sounds
like it's also a good idea to integrate
those continuous integration platforms
that you have and and add them to that
ruling is that something that you're
aiming for there are quite a few
commercial commercial offerings that are
provided exactly that and then you would
end up with using that commercial
offering inside the cloud somewhere
instead of provisioning your own as he
CI server at that point yeah definitely
definitely the whole project flux is is
based on an architecture that is very
open and that people can can connect to
that with their own components so they
can they can build their own bits of
pieces and they can connect their own
systems so this this flux environment I
can I can talk about the technical
details later but it's it's perfectly
built for this setting that I'm
connecting my project I'm working on my
code in the browser window and someone
else is oh I provide you with an
additional service for your project like
if you if you hit this button it's
automatically being pushed into the CI
system or it's automatically built or
it's automatically deployed to a
platform as-a-service thing and then not
everything is being rebuilt for for the
cloud because there are already existing
existing tools like that or you're
connecting your projects to git
repositories and things like that yeah
yeah that's definitely possible and
something we we're trying to build this
kind of it's an in it's more or less an
infrastructure for connecting the
different bits and pieces together in a
cloud-based environment okay so one of
the questions if you talk about cloud
it's usually also that there are
questions around data privacy so what do
you think about that I mean it's then an
issue because obviously you're sharing
the source code with certain services
that are out there run and that are run
by different people so what about that
yeah
the idea behind flux is um and I already
mentioned something like it's a little
bit like Dropbox for code it's its first
it says let's say it's a single user
system so it is it does not try to
replace version control systems or
whatever so when I connect my project to
flux it's my project and I can access my
project and no one else even other
people from my team are the members
they're not able to access myself if
they if they're working on the same
project they can connect their project
as well which is maybe the same but they
can connect their projects well and they
have their space I have my space in
inside flux inside this cloud
environment and if I if I would like to
use certain services that in that case
need access to my stuff that I synced
with with flux I could imagine that it's
not yet yet implemented but the idea is
in the design is built in that way that
you you have to allow and enable those
services to say ok you service XYZ you
can now access my stuff so you enable
those services yourself instead of they
are kind of secretly magically behind
the scenes grabbing your stuff from
somewhere in the cloud I think some of
that or bits pieces that will be
integrated and implemented in these
basic fundamental infrastructure that we
build for flux because these data
syncing mechanism for you can sync your
files like Dropbox for code that's a
fundamental part of flux and it's not
only interestingly it's not only syncing
files and when you press save the safe
is being synced to the chain
just being tuned it's also sinking
changes while you are typing so you can
you can sync your stuff on these kind of
safe and don't worry and commit level
but it's also sinking while you are
typing so while you're typing inside
your IDE everything is being synced with
the cloud immediately in real-time the
same happens for the browser editor so
in that case you could even imagine
saying oh I have my desktop ID my clips
IDE open I type in my my code someone
interrupts you or power goes down
whatever you're offline and if you
switch to another machine you open up
the web browser you will see exactly the
same state without saving the file first
in address type ID you will see exactly
the same state and in the web-based
editor and that's kind of a an
additional feature on a digital syncing
level inside flux and that's also being
used by these kind of the the services
that are running that will provide you
with these language tooling
yes one's really interesting so talking
about the architecture what what is it
how is that system built out put out
some some the confrontations the
technology foundations and so on of that
system yeah the the core idea behind
that is the backbone of everything is a
messaging system so everything is being
built on top of asynchronous messages
there is no REST API inside the whole
system there are no HTTP calls that we
made there are services but those
services they do not provide a restful
api or something like that so they're
basically the main thing is there's
these kind of you can connect components
to this messaging system you can send
messages around and that is what the
Eclipse Rd for example or our plugin for
the Eclipse IDE or for any IDE doesn't
it's not a club specific really so not
specifically Eclipse IDE you can also
imagine doing the same stuff for
IntelliJ whatever is connecting to this
messaging system and it's sending
messages forth and back and that's
basically it right that's there's
everything and there is another
component running in the cloud that is
also connecting this mess
just listening to messages sending
messages for them back and the sinking
mechanism that I described these kind of
Dropbox code thing and real-time edit
syncing that's built on top of those
messages so while you're typing in your
IDE they are sending messages forth and
back and while you're typing inside the
browser window sending messages for
stand back when you press safe this
message being sent for sandbag and with
for sandbag I mean it there's a message
being sent to all the participants in in
let's say in myspace right of course not
saying to everybody in the world but to
all the components that are connected to
my to my files basically and on top of
this let's say file or data syncing
mechanism on these while typing level or
safe level and they can other components
in running in the cloud that can also
connect to this messaging system and
syncing the data locally to their
environment and this is what what
happens for implementing a language
tooling so the the browser-based editor
in this case doesn't know anything about
Java really maybe it knows about syntax
highlighting but nothing else it doesn't
even maybe doesn't even really know what
Java is or how Java works or how
contents this works for Java or how
error reporting works instead there is a
service it's tiny little service you can
even maybe call it micro service running
inside the cloud that is connecting to
this message bus and this service is
it's keeping track of those changes as
well so while you're typing it mirrors
those changes locally to its service
environment and I can do something with
these files and with these changes so in
in the case of for example Java there's
a Java reconciling service and this
reconciling service keeps track of those
changes those reconciling and sends back
the errors and warnings that the service
produced sends those errors and warnings
back to the messaging system so those
let's say the results of the service are
being sent back to everybody and the
code editor in the browser just consumes
those messages and say oh there's a
that's an error and warning report for
this hire that I have opened oh I can
show that and this creates a very
loosely coupled environment because
every service can now decide on its own
what it would like to do the Java
service can say oh I can do reconciling
for Java or I can do content assist for
Java for example because the
browser-based editor since out oh I need
contents is but I have no idea how to do
contents for this file there's a service
a I can do content assist and then it
sends back a message about continent
system and this is I think very very
interesting ok this sounds really
interesting it's sort of sounds to me
sort of like a component model and
obviously the question is whether that's
will hide one point replace the Eclipse
plugin mechanism as it exists today it's
an interesting question because I think
the whole the whole idea behind this
asynchronous messaging and the way those
services are being implemented in flux
is is kind of completely different from
the plugin mechanism for the Eclipse IDE
or the plugin mechanism that you might
be familiar with for other ideas or
other tools this is the case because in
the in the in the Eclipse world and the
Eclipse plugin world you have the
Eclipse platform implementation and all
the plugins and they provide some kind
of API and some kind of interfaces and
whatever and you implement plug-in by
calling those interfaces or implementing
interfaces calling the existing platform
API so you have more or less you have to
implement your stuff with Java and some
in some cases it's it's a little bit
strange right if you if you do C++
tooling for Eclipse you implement C++
tooling in Java right you've write C++
tooling in Java or if you would like to
support Java Script you write your
language tooling for JavaScript in Java
and that's sometimes it's a little bit
strange right in flux it's completely
different because there is no platform
API there is no API to call not even a
restful api as I already said and
instead those services that are
participating the syncing mechanism the
only the only thing they need to know
about the environment
is they are connecting to this message
system so they are getting messages
right and they can send out messages and
of course the format of this map of
those messages that's kind of defined
and needs to be defined so this is some
kind of a protocol or some kind of an
API contract but it's not exactly
calling one thing right it's you
understand it interpret those messages
um and therefore each service can decide
on its own how it would like to be
implemented so as I mentioned before
there's a Java reconciling service for
example that does these errors and
warnings for Java or a Java continously
service so this specific tiny little
service can say okay I'm implemented in
Java I'm running on OSGi I'm and I'm
reusing the Eclipse Java compiler for
example to do the job right you do not
have to re-implement everything you can
reuse the existing parts that are there
for this time little service right for a
different service you can you can go a
totally different different way for
example if you would like to do the same
for JavaScript so there's a fire being
edited and their message is coming run
Oh someone is editing a JavaScript file
and the Java service would of course say
I have no idea about that file so I just
ignore those messages but the other
micro service about JavaScript can say
oh I can give you errors and warnings
for JavaScript and I'm implemented in
JavaScript myself so I'm running on for
example I'm writing a no js' inside the
cloud and I'm reusing jslint or another
JavaScript library doing these errors
and warnings for JavaScript and that's I
think that visualizes these highly
decoupling among those services and that
each service can decide on its own what
to do with those messages what messages
to send back how to react to certain
messages what files it would like to
sync so not every service needs to sink
every files right there gonna be so say
oh I'm just interested in these Java
files and I'm interested in binary files
or whatever and another source could
decide it could make it totally
different decision about that you can
you can choose your own give you the
language and the environment you
like to use and you can even maybe host
the service in a totally different data
center if you want because the only
thing you need is this connection with a
message bus so for example we talked
before about connecting something like a
CI system for example to flux so there
could be a service listening to those
messages and say oh whenever you press
save I trigger a CI built and the
service is not running inside the same
let's say data center or cloud
environment as maybe the the syncing
mechanism or the the code editor but
it's running inside the data center of
the company who is providing the CI
build system right and it's just
connecting to flux so that they can take
care about hosting and scaling or
whatever doing with this service
basically on their own and decide how to
implement that and this is I think also
very interesting for supporting all
these different languages because you
can implement a service that's able to
do job holding another one can do
javascript a third one can do scala the
fourth one can do whatever or you can
even say oh I have a super service it's
able to do content sis for these ten
different languages if you have that
that piece and you can especially reuse
existing parts that's I think they're
important because I I really would like
to see awesome Java language tooling in
the cloud but I definitely do not want
to re-implement a Java compiler or the
whole Eclipse Java tooling in JavaScript
again because I would like to run it
inside a browser window right that's
that then maybe that could work but it's
not something I would like to do instead
I'm employing this cloud service is
listening to those messages
implementing that functionality and
reusing existing price for example in
this case of Eclipse and running parts
of the Eclipse Java tooling in a
headless way inside a cloud inside a
cloud environment I think that's a very
very interesting outcome of these basic
fundamental architecture and idea behind
flux because it's created a completely
highly decoupled environment
and therefore it also kind of replaces
this plugin architecture alpha clothes
maybe it's the the plugins for flux are
more these cloud services that are
running and connecting to the messaging
system and that's it maybe that's the
kind of the if you would call it I would
never call a plugin mechanism but it's
it's the mechanism for collaboration
among services and different people
adding different functionality yeah that
sounds really really interesting and
it's it's a very good vision I think for
the future of IDs so what state is that
project in right now I mean what can I
actually do with it who is working on it
and are there some bits and pieces that
I can already touch the project is being
created at eclipse and at the moment we
are contributing the the initial code
for that and the initial code which is
at the moment available from a different
repository of github but it's already
open sourced and that's a prototype and
the prototype and all the the purpose of
the prototype was to do some kind of a
proof-of-concept so the prototype is
able to send project with a cloud from
your existing desktop Eclipse IDE doing
life edit changes and it's doing a
little bit of of Java language support
for errors and warnings just content
assist does navigation and rename it
file those are the basic features that
we implemented for the prototype to do
some kind of proof of concept
it's nothing you can download at the
moment and reuse in production because
it's it's just a prototype so the next
steps will be to build something that
says something real out of this
prototype code so we will I think we
will definitely maybe re-implement parts
of the of the underlying infrastructure
to make it more reliable more robust
more scalable because the prototype is
just built on on WebSockets and Jason is
just being sent around so and in socket
IO or nodejs so maybe it's not I don't
know maybe it is the choice that we will
we will also make it the future but
maybe we also use different things like
rabbit and cue and using mqtt or
whatever so there are
certain questions still open and so we
we need to build it let's say the real
thing
next therefore it's not you can you can
use the existing prototype you can play
around with it if you want it's a bit
it's a bit rough to set up but but you
can you can you can get it to work you
can use that and you can you can play
around with it to get a feeling about
what does it mean to build these
microservices for these ide kind of
environment and there's even one guy who
already started doing that huh got
for me team as he he took the prototype
college and say oh i would like to
support XTX next extent as a language so
let's let's see what's necessary to do
that and he implemented the service that
is doing exactly that
during consensus and reconciling for 4x
text which i think is awesome it's
greater then shows that and kind of
proves that a little bit that it is
indeed as open as we would like it to be
and as powerful as I envisioned it to be
so besides you who is working on this
what is the team like so we as a tooling
team at pivotal we are working on that
and so there are a bunch of bunch of
guys at pivotal working on that in
addition to the work we're doing for the
spring tool speed and for the existing
eclipse based IDE s and there are quite
a number of coming of initial committees
from IBM I think most of them are
working on Eclipse Orion at the moment
because they are very very interested in
connecting Orion to this architecture to
enable Orion to do language tooling or
to implement language tune for wine that
is for Java or for more complicated
languages and they are also very
convinced and their interest in this
flux architecture and so they are also
working on flux building this
infrastructure and building Java
language tooling maybe even JavaScript
language tooling as this kind of initial
idea to do these kind of show people how
to do language tooling or based on flux
so that other people can jump in and
there may even other companies already
said are we
like redhead is interested in ETS is
interested and few other people say oh
yeah
we are very interested in this project
we would like to contribute and become
commuters maybe in the future so and
many other people said oh yeah this is
really interesting so I think it's there
will be a lot of people joining and we
are very open so if you're interested in
joining the project it would like to
contribute feel free to send us email
join discussions on the mailing list we
are we are very very open to new
committees and contributors very happy
to collaborate yeah sounds great
M so you already mentioned it too so
Ryan can you talk a little bit about
that project and how it relates to the
flux
yeah the Eclipse Orion project um that
goal is to do some kind of browser-based
tooling platform and they very much at
least from my point of view they very
much focus on the client side of these
cloud-based ITES so what what they did
is they implemented it's more or less a
full-featured cloud IDE already and
maybe not providing 5 million features
but the good set of features focusing on
JavaScript tooling and CSS and HTML so
therefore these kind of Webley world and
most of the stuff that they've
implemented is based on running every
site everything inside the browser
window in JavaScript so they implemented
the JavaScript framework and JavaScript
libraries and JavaScript components for
doing this code editing they have an
awesome code editor that's running
inside the browser window it's even
faster and the Eclipse code editor
running on your desktop IDs it's really
amazing what's possible in the in the
browser today and those components are
more they running inside the browser
window and implemented JavaScript and
this is to me feels like an awesome
combination that could come out of these
combination of doing the Orion side for
doing the Orion using the right
components and the rhein IDE for the
client side and connecting that with
flux to bridge Oh Ryan to existing
desktop IDs because at the moment Ryan
as I said before
at the beginning is also this kind of
completely disconnected environment it's
purely running inside the cloud so the
flux could provide an awesome way to
connect Orion to exist in testimonies
with these syncing mechanism and in
addition to that flux could also be used
to do more advanced language tooling for
Ryan that you would not like to do like
you would not like to implement Java
language tooling in JavaScript for Ryan
and so on so flux could be used to
implement exactly that so I think it's a
could be an awesome combination using or
I connected to flux and maybe even other
other backends and and and other UI's as
well so okay yeah sounds like there's a
lot of synergy to be there am so I mean
there is quite a huge community around
eclipse so have you already presented
that a project to e to the Eclipse
community what are the responses how's
that taken up by by the Eclipse projects
are there any other collaborations to
other projects besides Orion we haven't
formally set up other collaborations to
other projects yet I think the the
interest from attainments and the XX
guys is already showing that they are
interested in there and I very much hope
to collaborate deeply with them in the
future we presented the project at
Eclipse con and this year and the
feedback was really awesome so people
really liked it and I was very happy to
hear that and we were we were joining
magma liquid for his keynote at Eclipse
console he we had a kind of five minute
guest appearance in the keynote showing
a demo of flux and the reaction from the
press and from other communities and
from other people inside the Eclipse
community was totally positive and they
they all said oh this is awesome so I I
hope to fulfill all the expectations of
course with the project and I think
there are a lot of other people will
show up and say hey this is interesting
can we can be joined and I would be very
very happy about that okay so you
already got your five minutes of fame it
so um if you if if I look at the itec
trend and how you describe the
architecture it sounds a lot like
Microsoft's micro services that are
becoming quite fashionable these days
and this concept seems to be seems to
originate from e-commerce websites where
you would cut down your system to
specific parts and have them integrated
in your in your e-commerce website what
I find interesting is that you are
applying these principles to a
completely different environment with
IDs so how is this different what what
does that mean and why does it really
make sense in this environment as well
because I mean obviously IDs are highly
interactive tools and it's somewhat
different from an e-commerce website
where basically all the systems are in
one data center usually and there is a
lot less latency and so on
oh yeah that's a that's a big question I
think that first of all the the
fundamental idea behind micro services
about cutting down your existing
e-commerce system or existing enterprise
system into small bits and pieces and
and make that available its individual
pieces of functionality that totally
makes sense and I think we are kind of
trying to to do the same with the
existing IDs right
we are we're trying to we're building
these micro services and we are trying
to reuse existing parts that already
exist and I think doesn't make sense to
throw everything away that we have at
the moment in it that's why the ease
because they have I don't know 20 years
of experience for doing awesome laughs
Java language tooling or language
tooling for other languages so it
definitely makes sense to reuse that so
therefore I I totally follow the same
line with with these micro services for
for flux
cutting down existing des parties into
small micro services maybe implementing
new micro services using different
libraries combining that with other
existing libraries and reusing a lot of
code
instead of reimplemented everything and
to me that makes total sense and
decoupling those bits of pieces also
makes makes a lot of sense because as
usual and software engineering
decoupling is usually a good idea right
what I think there is still a difference
in difference between these these micro
services that are discussed at the
moment so famously because usually
people associate with micro services
this is some kind of an API that you
call from outside right so there's a
service that service provides a certain
functionality use that feature provides
it with a specific API maybe in it's a
restful api or some other way and then
you call that you know there is the
service you call it from the outside
because you know it's there with flux we
we do it differently
because we're doing it with these
asynchronous messages and so it's more
service is more opting into the system
and say oh I'm interested in this I can
I can give something back
I can consume messages and I can send
messages back as a result so there is no
formal API contract between for example
the code editor is not calling the Java
service to say hey do something with
this file if the Java source a I can do
something for this file sending back
messages and the address a I display
those messages the editor doesn't care
about what service is providing these
error messages for example and I think
this is a an interesting difference
because it allows us to decouple the
system even more which i think is very
important in this case because in the
for for IDs and language tooling you
usually would like to be very open for
different languages and different
frameworks and you would like to support
five million different bits and pieces
and you would like to allow people to
add more language support for different
languages in the future without changing
all the other parts right you would not
like to change the editor just because
someone would like to support Erlang or
whatever for the system right and with
flux you can just basically implement
the Erlang micro service
maybe even in Erlang who knows
connecting the system and then sending
sending back those messages I think
that's a kind of a difference to what's
usually being associated with micro
services at the moment but the
fundamental idea about a micro service
is I think very much the same and to me
that that then totally makes sense for
for an ideal world yeah and let me just
add that interestingly enough even
though rest is somewhat famous in
particular for micro service probably
it's really the case that are quite a
few other applications that also use
this message oriented approach as well
however what I'm wondering is I mean
what you're basically saying is it makes
a lot of sense to have a synchronous
message based communication between
parts that ultimately together form an
IDE but if you look at the Eclipse placa
mechanism I mean it's obviously based on
interfaces and the usgi concept
including bundles and so on so M what do
you think I mean has this plugin concept
somehow failed or was it the wrong
approach or why it's to me coming from
an eclipse perspective you should really
have taken that approach to the cloud
shouldn't you because that's what
Eclipse ultimately does so there must be
some reason for you to shift to this
different approach yeah that's an
interesting question because I think I
think the Eclipse plugin mechanism and
dlci model underneath it it's in totally
awesome mechanism and I think it was it
wasn't a huge step forward at the time
it was invented for Eclipse was a huge
step forward because if you compared it
to the IDE said that we had before the
Eclipse the Eclipse IDE they were these
huge monolithic things that are built
for one one language and if you would
like to add tooling like oh I would like
to support a JSP file it would basically
blow up the whole system because could
not really be implemented in
in that environment before eclipse so I
think the Eclipse packing mechanism was
a huge step forward in and as he see
from from all the millions of packets
are available it was a huge success and
I still believe that that's great right
it also creates a set of problems and
you you the certain challenges involved
like creating a unique hue I experience
and a good integration at the UI without
screwing up context menu saying oh I
have five million plugins installed and
then I had five million entries in the
menu and you need to scroll down or
things like that um but I think that's
that's not that's not an issue with the
mechanism itself right it's it's it's an
issue with how do people use that and
how do people take care of the overall
experience instead of just focusing on
the one plugin that they are building
for flux we we try to do things
differently not because we were thinking
oh the old thing it doesn't work but
because we thought let's try to to
attack this issue this problem this
challenge from a totally different point
of view and explore something totally
different to think about new ways to
build build stuff and new ways to to do
this and especially in this cloudy
environment you have a lot of things are
different right you have maybe a network
in between you have you have components
running inside a cloudy environment you
would like to scale up cloudy components
and you have you do not have these
there's one system and one user
relationship so you have the cloud
service maybe is should be able to serve
thousands or hundreds of thousands of
users at the same time and and I think
that maybe the triggers are thought and
made us think about should we try to do
things differently and that's why we we
try to do things complete as a first
step completely different in a
completely different way to explore what
could come out of that and that's why we
chose this this messaging system because
we thought oh yeah this messaging
in the communication between browsers
and cloud services let's try to explore
that and try to go the extreme way to
find out does it really work or is it
just a crazy idea and to me it feels
like this could really work in an
awesome way I think that's that's a
reason it's not really not not saying
anything against the Eclipse plugin
mechanism or whatever I think it's still
Nasim awesome awesome idea for the for
the purpose it was built for okay so and
the other question that comes to mind is
and if I look at IDs
I mean it's highly interactive
environment and what you've described
this rather distributed system so you
would even have some service somewhere
giving returning some kind of error
messages and that might run somewhere on
the internet and then this is combined
with an as Acronis communication
mechanism but which also increases
latency so I would be pretty afraid that
you end up with the system with rather
high latency that you cannot really
afford to have a good experience for the
user so what do you think is that going
to be an issue or what do you think
about it I think it's going to be an
interesting challenge and we try to
explore this space a little bit with the
prototype and what we found out is that
even doing kind of contents is and
errors and warnings for real-time
editing I'm doing this with well with
the service and with it with an
messaging system that's running on some
kind of cloud provided infrastructure
somewhere in some Amazon data center
connected with a crappy Wi-Fi at a
conference for example to the system
even in that case it worked very nicely
and it provided a good user experience
of course there there could be Network
latency issues in between like if the
network is crappy and in slow you might
not get the the best experience out of
that that that's that's correct
an interesting side effect is that you
could there could be multiple instances
of those services running in the cloud
and the interesting thing is if
those instances of the service are
running in different data centers they
can all work at the same time because
they can all work in parallel right
we're just completely different from
desktop by the ease where you have to
build in these kind of parallel
execution of stuff right that's they can
all execute at the same time inside the
cloud and the first guy who sends back
the errors mornings that guy wins right
so as a side effect of the architecture
without really building that as a
feature into the system as a side effect
and if you are sitting in in the US and
there is the Java source is running
inside the US Amazon data center east
and one is running inside West and one
is running inside the Asia data center
and they are all doing the same stuff at
the same time you would see the errors
as soon as the first guy sends you that
information back so you will always kind
of get the best experience independent
of where you are it still depends on the
network right and the other the other
answer to that question is that I think
the there are two use cases for this or
two let's say two environments for this
one is what you you already kind of said
is there is this hosted service running
on the internet somewhere and he used
that and you can use that and to use
that you need to have good internet
connection with maybe low low latency
that's but I think that's just one use
case that's maybe suitable for certain
settings but not for everything and
maybe not for big companies for big
companies I could also imagine and think
that's very reasonable to do it
differently and follow these kind of the
github enterprise model where you host
the whole thing inside your own data
center inside your own company inside
your own network right and in that case
network latency is usually not not such
an issue because you have fastened fast
connection to your own data center to
your own network anyway and you keep
everything inside your company so it's
not going outside of your company it's
not going to someone but someone else
you can host everything on your own it's
also giving you a little bit of answer
to these kind of security questions so
are you afraid of someone else accessing
your code if you're hosting everything
tell you on data center you can be sure
that it's only accessed by your employ
isn't up or someone else and that would
also help to to provide a good
experience but but even in the case
where we tried it from this crappy
conference Wi-Fi and even on a cell
phone connection this 4g cell phone
connection which usually has some kind
of a higher latency than than usual even
in that case it worked and it worked
nicely so that that convinced me and
other people saw that demo saying yeah
this could be interesting and and the
prototype that we used for that wasn't
even optimized in any way it wasn't
optimized for small small message to
send around or less data sent around or
whatever was a the project that you can
you can download from github it's quite
interesting because we just had a
discussion I think even today and I
think we what we basically agreed on was
that for micro services it's actually
probably a good idea to have the micro
service provide the the graphical user
interface so that you can work around
those latency issues because then if you
have like like a vertical part of your
system including the graphical user
interface as one service then you don't
have a lot of pieces talking to each
other it's one request HTTP requests for
that matter will just be done by one
micro service and what you're saying is
that even though the application has
sort of a distributed layer layer
architecture it still works
yeah and I think I think what's um
what's an interesting detail about the
flux architecture with regards to these
kind of exchanging data so one is that
there are different levels right and
this there is not this redditor and the
editor is working on code and when
whenever you change something it's hands
over the code to a service the service
is analyzing the file and sending you
begging for me
that's not the case right instead it's
zoomed all the time independent of what
you're trying to do next so that each
service has all the time the the latest
state of your resources circuit with
these mechanism in that case if you for
example press content assist the editor
doesn't need to send over the
information about the file content or
the project whatever over to the service
the only thing it needs to send over the
wire is give me consciousness for this
file so the path of the idea of this
file at this position that's it doesn't
need to to submit the whole content of
the file and anything anything in
addition to that and I think that's an
interesting interesting detail because
it allows each service to operate
locally on the data because it it
remains kind of it or it keeps a copy of
the data synced all the time and can
operate locally on that data
therefore these kind of exchanging data
all the time and sending a huge bunch of
data sports and PEG which might be an
issue with with the the traditional
e-commerce or Enterprise Service that's
that's that's often different different
way because you basically know about the
syncing mechanism under the hood yeah
okay sounds interesting it's arrogant
but quite an interesting application of
Microsoft's as pattern I would say so
it's just limited to the Eclipse IDE are
you seeing any interest from other ID
projects out there or what's what's your
comment on that I haven't heard anything
from from from from the NetBeans or
IntelliJ or whatever other IDE saying oh
we would like to participate yet but the
whole the whole flux architecture and
the whole system is not tied to eclipse
at all to be honest at the prototype not
even the prototype is very much tied to
eclipse because the only bit that we
inject into the Eclipse IDE for flux is
a tiny little plugin for Eclipse that
allows the Eclipse workspace to
participate in the sink
mechanism so sinking changes while
you're typing or when you're saving file
you can I'm sure I've done it yet but
I'm sure you can very easily build
exactly the same plugin for IntelliJ
IDEA
for NetBeans or even for your file
system that if you prefer to work with
Emacs you can even have some kind of
demon watching on your faster so maybe
the while typing is more difficult in
that case but for this synciq file
changes that can easily be impressed on
the file system without without knowing
anything about the Eclipse IDE so flux
is definitely not about connecting the
Eclipse IDE only to this cloudy world it
opens up this mechanism for all the
different IDE so if someone from from
NetBeans would like to join the party
very welcome okay great is there
anything that I forgot to ask you any
other comments you want to make um no I
I don't think so I think we covered most
of the interesting questions maybe I've
got I forget something as well but I
would like to repeat the these my my
sentence about we are very open if you
would like to join the project if you
would like to contribute if if you would
like to connect different IDE provide a
service or whatever feel free to reach
out to us we are it's not tied to
eclipse at all so in your view we are
very open so please contact us and then
we would be happy to collaborate after
me it also sounds like if you actually
reach the goal and when you realize that
vision there is why I mean it will
probably give rise to a marketplace
where you could actually well sell
subscriptions to specific services so I
think it really sounds quite interesting
yeah could be I haven't thought about
that that I think I haven't thought
about a commercial aspect of that yes
but I think there certainly a lot of
possibilities open up there yeah okay
thanks a lot for talking to us and it's
great to have you on the show thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about this on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog if you
have feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so that other listeners can respond
to your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]